[music]
Heat. Heat.
Heat. Heat. N.
[music]
Heat. Heat.
Hello and welcome to the .NET AI
community standup. Um, I'm John
Galloway. I am your guest host today
because Bruno is in Boston.
>> Yes. Oh my god, you make me feel so bad.
That's how you are supposed to start the
show. I always start to do talking
something about hey this is amazing and
more introduce yourself and no thanks
everyone and thanks Steve also to be
here. I'm really looking forward to
learn more about this and I only going
to be here for two minutes and then
switch to the chat because as you see
not in the standard office I am in the
middle of post on also supporting
another event. So thanks a lot also John
for helping hosting this because the the
SDK is super cool man I am building so
small and crappy application so much fun
I'm having with this and it's amazing I
love it. All right. And we are both very
excited to be joined by Steve today to
talk about the CLI and the SDK for .NET
developers.
>> Hello.
>> Awesome. Well, I have just a few
community links I'll share and then
we'll turn it over to you. Um, so let me
share my screen
and that is this one here. Okay. And
add stage. There we go. All right. So we
have uh last week we had a fun exciting
announcement. This was using the um the
SDK with work IQ. Um so this is this is
a really neat example of connecting your
um all your communications and all your
kind of business intelligence uh you
know whether that's SharePoint or
anything that goes on you can think of
like the Microsoft graph. So, this
connects all that context as an MCP
server and um you'll see some neat
examples. There's some demo videos um
showing this and uh things like
generating an architecture diagram based
on conversations which is which is
mind-blowing. And then Burke has a
really cool uh video where he does where
he um he talks about building a VS Code
extension that does some things like
pull in uh upcoming meetings and
documents and things that he's going to
need to review before those meetings. So
this that's he I love his scenario
because he's like I'm deep in this, you
know, I'm like I'm deep in my code. I'm
coding away. All of a sudden no, I got a
meeting coming up and it like inside of
VS Code has something popping up telling
you about that. So, uh, information in
here about how to get set up for that.
Um, and you'll see, uh, it's configured
as an MCP server. I helped behind the
scenes on this post, so I got to, uh, do
a little Easter egg in here and put make
sure my name was featured at least once
in the post. So, so that is that thing.
Um, another neat thing, we just had a
blog post go out this morning. This is
from Jeremy. Um here he's talking about
uh he's starting a series on the core
building blocks of .NET AI essentials.
So he's starting here with MEAI and he's
going to be going through vector data
agent framework and MCP. So this uh he's
he's done some other posts on this just
kind of like stepping back and let's
look at the fundamentals. A lot of the
time we get really kind of like uh you
know we'll say hey here's a new release
it adds all these great new features and
we've got some folks that are saying
like hey step back a bit and just
explain the bigger context and so that's
what this series does. So excited to see
the rest of these as they go out. One
other just random grabag thing here.
This was something that I just saw come
by in a chat yesterday. It's a public
PR, so feel like I'm okay to share it.
But this is um this is a neat thing. Uh
adding into the agent framework exposing
an AI agent implementation of the GitHub
copilot SDK. So it took me a little bit
to wrap my mind around this one here,
but general idea is being able to um
treat the GitHub Copilot SDK as an
agent, be able to include it in tasks
and workflows and all that kind of
stuff. So this is just a merge PR. It'll
go out at some point, but I just thought
that was a pretty neat thing. And um I'm
done. [laughter]
So, Steve, I guess should we turn it
over to you?
>> Yeah. All right. Brilliant. Well, I am
very happy to be here and to chat to
everybody about all this stuff. Um so,
we put the the to title down as using
Copilot CLI and SDK for .NET
development. And uh we of course will
talk about that but I also really want
to have a slightly broader conversation.
So quite a lot of what I going to will
show and talk about is not really going
to be net specific because it doesn't
need to be like when you're doing
agentic coding a lot of the time it
doesn't really make any difference what
language you're using and sometimes you
might not even know or care yourself.
Um, so you know, it's the the broader
set of concepts that I think are perhaps
a little bit more interesting right now.
And honestly, it feels like it's a big
moment in the whole history of software
that we're going through and I and I
want to like open up a slightly broader
conversation with with this group and
find out what people are feeling about
the whole thing um like and what
techniques uh uh and tips people have
got for for being successful as this new
world evolves. So, let me share my
screen and we'll start talking through
some of this stuff. And uh Bruno and
John, anytime you feel like it, by all
means, just interject and um we will uh
we'll discuss whatever you want. So,
I've got about half an hour or so of
content to go through. Um but, you know,
we can adjust as we go. I'm trying to
share my screen, but right now here we
go. Entire screen. As you're doing that,
I'll just funny side story, but
there is really an interesting thing
like you're saying at this moment where
the actual language or code itself is a
bit of an artifact
>> and I recently built um a single page
app and I built it with React and Vit
and hosted on GitHub pages. I'm not I'm
a net person. I barely like I feel very
uncomfortable building with those
languages and it worked just fine using
Copilot. It it was something that was
slightly smoother in this, you know,
using it with um GitHub pages hosting
and I was like shocked at like, yeah, it
all worked, you know, it was kind of
fun. So, all right, let me pop you down
to the screen.
>> All right. Okay. Right. So, let's think
about the the broad picture of what's
going on in the industry and in fact
what our industry even is like what do
we do all day? All right. So, let's
think of ourselves as software
developers. So um why did we get into
this in the first place? I imagine that
just about everyone on the call has got
some major things in common like we like
computers right it's very general point
but we do probably most of us since we
were kids and we like solving problems
using our brains we enjoy the entire
experience of thinking carefully about
stuff coming up with solutions and
designs and turning it into a real thing
that delights people in the external
world um and you know it's a good
lifestyle for us We get to hang around
with our computers, drink coffee, chat
to other nerds, and you know, solve
interesting problems. That's great.
We've all, you know, benefited a lot
from that. I know I have. Um, but stuff
feels a bit like it's changing right now
because up until this point, the we were
able to do this because we had a unique
ability that other people didn't. We
could create working code and other
people could not. But that's not really
the case anymore because now humans are
not the only things that can create
code, right? Machines can create code as
well now. And so the the landscape
around us is starting to change. So how
did this happen? Well, it all happened
really in the last couple years and and
I'm sure everyone here has seen it. So
um a bunch of products showed up in the
market in pretty quick succession. So uh
initially we had a wave of IDE and web-
based coding system coding agents. So uh
cursor showed us how it was possible to
add a bunch of AI powered uh coding uh
tools into an IDE. Pretty quickly after
that VS Code added its agent mode. So VS
Code already had a a co-pilot feature
but that was basically just AI
autocomplete. Uh and then agent mode
came along to turn that into something
that uh was able to tackle big problems
and go through a multi-step process to
solve things for you. And we had uh
GitHub Copilot on the web as well uh the
thing that's able to respond to your
comments and create pull requests for
you uh against your repo. And that's
changed the way that we were able to
produce code for the first time. But
then also a second wave came along and
believe it or not this was only just
from about six months ago. the the
arrival of the CLIs. So we had Claude
code came along and created this new
product category um of the the agent
experience inside a CLI which was pretty
quickly followed by uh Gemini CLI and
Codeex CLI and GitHub Copilot. And these
things have become incredibly popular.
Um they are popular perhaps because they
give you such a sense of immediacy.
They're not tied to a particular IDE or
particular concept of source control or
whatever. They can run in any directory.
You just pop them open, tell them what
they do, and they just start working.
And they're really addictive. Like some
people think of them as kind of like
dopamine machines. You just give it a
thing to like tell solve a problem for
me and like 5 seconds later, you've got
some kind of progress on that. So people
uh are very very enthusiastically
adopted these kinds of things. Okay. So,
I know that there's a mixture of
different opinions that people have
there uh about uh this kind of thing.
Some people on this call are going to be
very much into all this stuff and using
it all the time. Other people will be,
"Oh, I just haven't tried it yet." And
some people probably think, "Oh, I
actively dislike this this direction
that our industry is going in." Um, so I
think that what would be useful for us
is to go through some of the experience
of what it's like to do stuff with this
and and get into what are the ways that
we can be successful um with it and what
kind of questions does this bring up for
us about how we do our work and what
kind of future of an industry we're
creating for ourselves. Okay, so people
say that this gives them a phenomenal
increase in productivity. Now I don't
know whether you believe them or not but
I'm going to give you some stats from
the team that I work on. So I uh about
three four months ago or something I got
access to an early build of Copilot CLI
and I was so convinced by that that
within a couple of hours I started
making inquiries about going to move and
work on that team. And so that's what I
do now. Now I work on the co-pilot CLI
team and um we've
uh obviously very heavily adopted our
own products for our own work and this
[laughter] is just some stats I pulled
up this morning. So we've got a team of
about 7 to 10 people and we've shipped
over 200 things just in the last week.
Now that level of progress is for me
unheard of prior to this. Um, admittedly
some of those PRs are just like oneline
tweaks or documentation changes or
whatever, but I'd say realistically
we've shipped more than a hundred
non-trivial things in the last week. Um,
so yeah, it's absolutely making uh a
radical difference to us. And for anyone
who's not really tried it, I think it's
it's worth giving this a go. um to get a
quick experience of what that's like,
let's imagine that uh we're on the the
copilot uh CLI team right now and we
wanted to add a feature to the product.
Like how easy or hard would it be for us
to ship something? So let's say that we
want to have a way of knowing what
models, what AI models you can use
within Copilot CLI. And maybe we would
like there to be a command like copilot
show models. Now there isn't any command
like that right now. If you try and do
it, you're just going to get an error.
So, let's see if we can implement that
feature ourselves uh using copilot
obviously. So, we pop that open. We get
the classic um coding agent CLI view and
then we give it some instruction. So,
let's say uh add a show models command
to CLI that lists available models to
process standard out. and we will let
that get going. So obviously it's not a
very um complex instruction we've given
it. It's going to get working on
exploring that. You'll see that
initially it's decided to use a sub
agent here called explore. That's a
feature that we've uh only just
produced. So it's able to run background
tasks potentially in parallel. It's just
doing one here at the moment. So it's
got a specialized agent that knows how
to search the codebase and figure out
what to do. Um that has just completed.
So, what's it going to do now? Um, it's
looking through the rest of the code to
figure out where to put stuff. Um, it's
decided that it needs to decide where to
add the flag. Um, it's working out how
we register
flags
and it's continuing there. It's found an
example of something similar to that. uh
it's decided where okay it's made an
edit to the code already and now it
needs to add an actual implementation
for that. So let's just wait for it to
complete. All right it's decided it
wants to build the the CLI which it
does. What's it going to do next? It's
going to test that it actually works. So
it's running it itself to see what
output comes. It's decided that the
output is correct and it's finished. So
I've exited from there.
All right. So let's see what have we
got.
Let's do a get diff. We've now got All
right. So it's added this show models
and it's added a handler for that. It's
very very simple bit of code. Um but
let's see if it works.
It does. All right. Cool. So you know 30
seconds we've added our feature. Now you
might think okay but it's only like a
sixline feature. Uh that's true. It's
obviously very trivial. The hard part is
deciding where to add the six lines and
knowing that you're following all the
existing patterns correctly, but I hope
you give you a sense there of how it's
possible for each developer to ship like
10 features in a day. Um, obviously most
of them are going to be more
sophisticated than this, but uh it
definitely changes the experience of
producing code.
Okay. So,
this forces us to think differently
about how we produce software. Some of
the rules that we've been working with
for our entire careers up until this
point start to feel a little bit
different. So, one of the big changes is
now it feels like you can produce any
amount of code you want really quickly.
So, you don't have to be precious about
I I implemented something therefore we
have to ship it. We implement stuff all
the time and then don't ship it because
you know we change our minds about stuff
or we find a better way. When it comes
to prototyping,
you don't have to dedicate three days to
produce a prototype of most things. Now
you can do it in, you know, half an hour
if you're just doing something at
prototype quality. Um it it means that
we approach design in a different way.
In the past, we would think, okay,
before we invest a week's work into
something, we better have a series of
meetings to make sure we've got
consensus and have thought everything
through. We don't really do that
anymore. We just implement it possibly
multiple times in different ways to see
how it works out. And we learn by
actually doing something. When you've
actually got the feature implemented,
you can then think, well, does it
actually work well? Does it fit in with
the rest of the system? Do we have any
weird problems that we didn't
anticipate? and then we can just throw
it away if we do,
>> you know.
>> Do you mind if I jump in with a quick
question?
>> A lot of folks know you as the inventor
of Blazer and
>> I'm curious with this context how you
would think about
>> your the way that you prototyped and
built that if you had had co-pilot these
sort of tools available back then.
>> Yeah, I mean I guess it would have been
a lot faster and easier. I'm not saying
all of software is faster and easier.
We're going to get on to some of the
ways in which it's potentially even more
difficult and and and new problems might
occur. This is not just going to be like
pure sales pitch. I'll I'll point out up
front. Um but I would say that for the
for this specifically [laughter]
the task of building prototypes where
you don't have to care if all the
details are really right then absolutely
it would have been way way way faster.
Um, and probably a lot of details that
we had to leave until we could spend a
lot of time solving, we could have just
dealt with up front. Like, you know, it
took us so long to get debugger support
on web assembly. I maybe it would have
been there in the first week if you know
we could just throw a coding agent at
it. I don't know.
>> Wow.
>> Cool. All right. And hey, sorry I am
going to jump also here. By the way,
this is amazing. This is the fastest and
most amazing demo that I've seen in two
seconds of copilot CLI. So I love it. I
need to drop. And the last sentence is I
going to check the the YouTube channel
and comment there. You I love that you
said that this is the classic Copilot
CLI and it's been alive for a couple of
weeks, but it's already [laughter] the
classic one. It's it's everything is
moving so fast that I really enjoy I
really enjoy that having this is kind of
cool to do this. So hey, once again,
thanks everyone. See you all online and
see you next one. Awesome. All right.
Cool. So, changes the way we start to
think about things,
but some things might get harder for us.
And we don't yet know what we don't
know. Let's try and think through the
ways in which this might actually cause
problems for us, might make our jobs not
even what we want anymore to try and
anticipate where things going and try
and direct stuff so that it is what we
want and we can anticipate problems that
might otherwise occur. So, we'll get to
some of that as we go through this talk.
Now,
there are so many things going on with
coding agents. is incredibly hard to
keep track of all the different features
and capabilities and strategies and so
on that are available for people uh
using them. So some of the features here
that we've list actually I'll come back
to this in a minute. I'm going to give
do a demo of sub aents right now but it
takes a few minutes to run. So I want to
start that running and then we'll come
back to it in a second. All right so
let's just think about um a code review
scenario right that's a classic thing
that we all have to do. So, if I could
just get a browser up here. Um, so I I I
need to come up with something to code
review. So, um, here's an interesting
.NET project that I don't know if you've
all aware of. Um, it's an implementation
of the Doom game engine innet. And, uh,
it's all open source. It's all written
in C. It's pretty complicated codebase.
Like, it's a large and complicated
thing. Here's a pull request that came
in what, a few weeks ago. And if we go
in there, we say, "Oh, it's going to be
quite easy to review, isn't it? It's
only got two files changed." But then
you see those two files that have been
changed, and you think, "Oh my goodness,
who is going to review this? How am I
going to make sense of all that stuff?"
All right, what if there's a subtle bug
in all this math somewhere? Who's going
to spot that? Um, all right. So, let's
have a go at using Copilot to review
that. So, I'm in the um the game engine
source code here, and I'm going to go
into Copilot, and I'm going to get it to
do a review for me, but I'm going to do
it in a special way that you might not
have seen done before. So, I'm going to
say review the PR. I'll put the URL in,
but do it in parallel across Opus,
Haiku, and Gemini. All right, so those
are three different um agent models that
are available. Um, so Opus and Haiku are
both versions of Claude and Gemini is
um, Google's model. So that is going to
start looking at that pull request. It's
going to use the git commands to uh, to
get the details from GitHub. It's going
to start uh, checking out the diff. It's
doing an interesting technique here of
large output handling. So because we got
a large block of data back from this
pull request, 96 kilobytes, it's not
going to push all that into the context
window because it would start to, you
know, blow up the context window. So it
saves it to disk and then it can read
different parts of that. And once it's
got its bearings, it says now I'm going
to launch parallel code reviews with
different models. And so it started up
agents for Opus, Haiku, and uh Gemini 3
there. All right. Now, it might take a
minute for them to go through. So while
that does that, let's look at this
again. Right. So if you've been around
coding agents for more than a couple of
weeks, you will know that things are
changing very rapidly. Um these are a
bunch of features and as I look at this,
probably about half or more than half of
them have shipped in the last two weeks.
So like things are just moving so
quickly, it's hard to keep track of. So
sub aents are a way that um copilot or
other coding agents can start up
subprocesses within themselves
potentially with different context
different models uh and check out the
results. Plan mode I'll do a demo of and
that's a way of guiding a large piece of
work up front. Skills are a way of
producing reusable um context that you
can uh download and share uh and gain
the ability to do particular tasks. I'll
do an example of that. Delegates a way
that we can start some work locally and
send it up into the cloud to be
continued if you don't want to use up
your uh local resources to do it.
Memories keep track of context across
different sessions and even across
different developers on your team. So
when one developer teaches it something
like this is how we like to write tests.
Then that knowledge will be picked up
for other developers on your team. Uh
hooks are a way of doing deterministic
callbacks when the agent does a thing so
that you can invoke your own like helper
code to like you know check that you're
happy with the tools that it's using or
whatever. MCP I'm sure most people have
heard of that. It's a way of plugging in
external tools. Uh infinite sessions are
a way of never running out of context
that we only just shipped about two
weeks ago. Um plugins are a way of
fetching things like hooks and skills
and so on. I'll demo that in a minute.
And this mention of git here is a
realization that a lot of us have come
to in the last few weeks that you don't
need to call run git yourself anymore.
Like you never have to solve your own
merge conflicts any now. You don't even
have to write your own PR descriptions.
You can just tell an agent to do it and
it will do that stuff. It's so
liberating to not write PR descriptions
or deal with anything to do with git
branching and merging and stuff. The
agent just does it all.
>> All right. you're mentioning that there
was a great comment on that earlier. Um,
>> uh, let me see from KJ Betts saying
automating the agent using the the
GitHub CLI and, um, I'm not sure if
that's intentional, but the there's the
GitHub CLI and the GitHub copilot CLI.
I've been using the GitHub CLI
automating and saying like use the
GitHub CLI to create an issue or
whatever, right? and like having that
abstraction like you're saying being
able to say
>> to talk not just to the git command line
but also the GitHub command line and
just say like use the GitHub command
line create this issue or whatever.
>> Yeah, absolutely. Yeah. Well, I spend
all my time inside Copilot CLI. So, I
would just say things like create a PR
from this. I don't tell it how to do
that. I don't say you have to use the GH
command or whatever. It it knows, you
know, it will figure that stuff out and
do a good job of it.
>> All right. So, our multi-agent review
has completed. So, we've got feedback
from Claude Opus, from Haiku, and from
Gemini. And they've all got slightly
different opinions. And this is a great
way of dealing with things like the risk
of hallucination. So, just because one
of them hallucinates doesn't mean the
others will, and they'll effectively be
checking each other. So, let's ask uh
how the uh results differ. So, I'm going
to say, what were the main
disagreements? and we'll ask our council
of AIS um you know what different
opinions they had about uh this
particular massive pull request. Okay,
so it says
um
Opus identified a bug while Haiku
concluded the logic was correct. Opus
was more rigorous. Gemini has an
architectural concern, but whether or
not it's a real bug depends on stuff. Uh
blah blah blah. Haiku was the most
lenient. Gemini was critical. Opus was
in the middle. So that actually matters
what I often see. So Gemini does tend to
be a bit fussier. It will point out a
lot of issues, even ones that are
debatable whether they're really issues.
Um Haiku is is the least smart of these
three and Opus just tends to, you know,
focus on things that really are real. So
uh it's a pretty nice way of being able
to combine uh the abilities across
multiple agents. Okay, so that's an
example of using sub aents there. All
right, but it's not just these things
that are being built into the uh CLIs
and IDEs themselves. People are starting
to create their own workflows on top of
it that become sort of higher level AI
capabilities. Um, and this is where it
all starts to get really hard to keep
track of. So, uh, in the last few weeks,
we've seen things come out like this.
So, Gas Town, Steve Yaggi is a guy who's
been well known in the in the software
industry for many years, and he's been
exploring this way of creating this like
fictional town of AI agents where you've
got a mayor and convoys that send beads
to agents and, you know, they all
collaborate to work together on your
projects. It's sort of wild and
experimental, but you know, this sort of
thing people are are getting interested
in. And another thing that you might
well have heard of, this was incredibly
hot about two weeks ago for maybe 3 days
was Ralph Wigum. U I'm sure many of you
are thinking, what on earth is going on?
Why are you talking about Ralph Wigum in
this context? Well, um so Jeffrey
Huntley came up with this observation
that AI agents tend to be pretty lazy,
right? You you give it a task like, you
know, do these six things and it will do
four of them and it will say, I've done
four of the six things. I'm finished.
And you say what? do the other two. And
it says, "Okay, sure, I will." And then
it will go, "The other two are quite
hard. We'll leave those as a future
task." And you say, "No, I want you to
do them now." And it says, "You're
right. I will do them." And then it
goes, "I've added some to-do comments to
say that we will do these in the
future." And it's just ridiculous and
annoying. So, the Ralph Wigan concept is
a way of forcing the agent to just never
give up. It's literally just a while
loop that keeps saying, "No, keep
working. No, keep working." and you you
leave it running overnight and then you
know hopefully it's done a massive
amount of work in the morning. Uh people
say that they've done like big projects
like this like take an entire web
browser and port it to Rust or something
like that. Um kind of mad. Uh but
anyway, this is the sort of thing that
people are come up coming up with. It's
really interesting, but it's also
impossible to keep track of and you
never know which of these things is
really worth learning about. And it it
does create this quite difficult sense
of pressure for us as developers that
like how am I really going to keep up to
date on all this stuff? Um you know if
it was hard enough to keep track of all
the JavaScript frameworks, this is this
is on another level. So to minimize some
of the FOMO effect, let's do a bit of a
step back and think about some of the
the fundamentals and understand what's
really worth doing uh amongst all this
stuff.
Sorry, one sec.
Uh, John, can you still hear me?
>> I do.
>> You do? Okay. Right. Sorry. Everything
just went weird on my computer. All
right. Let's trust that we're good and
we can keep going. All right. So let's
think about some of the fundamentals if
you want to be successful uh working
with coding agents. So here are some of
the things that I think that we have
observed are genuinely effective. These
are like the treasures amongst all the
many many different um tools and
techniques and it's basically the same
sort of things that are successful if
you want to be successful as a human.
Um, so most of the time that uh work
with AI agents fail, it's usually
because the task you've given it is
underspecified and AI agents are
unbelievably lazy. If there's any way
they can avoid doing the work and just
doing it in a rubbish cheap way instead,
they usually will. So planning is a a
process that a lot of people go through
in order to ensure they've really
specified what they want up front. and
it became popular enough that it ended
up becoming uh a native tool in many of
the AI uh CLI tools and it is in copilot
CLI. So I'm going to show you an example
of that right now. So over here I've got
another .NET project called Simple
Commerce and this is like the most
classic mainstream uh business scenario
I can possibly think of. It's a classic
e-commerce site. So this is totally
normal e-commerce with the only
exception that the sample prices are
utterly outrageous and for some reason
it just switches from language, you
know, between different languages in the
middle. Other than that, it's a
completely normal e-commerce website.
Let's say I want to add some
sophisticated feature to this. Here's
how we can do it. Uh using the planning
feature that's just been shipped a
couple of weeks ago. So let's go into
co-pilot here.
Right. So you'll see that we've now got
this shift tab to cycle mode that we've
just added. And if I do a shift tab,
then I am going to switch into planning
mode. Right? So I'm in plan mode now.
And that means that when I give it some
instruction like uh add a product
customization feature. Normally it would
just go ahead and start writing some
code. But because I'm in plan mode, it
knows I just want to work through the
process of designing this. So, it's
going to start thinking about that. It's
going to work out what might be meant by
this. It's doing an exploration of the
codebase and it's decided to ask me a
question. What type of product
customization do you have in mind? Uh,
we got various options. I can type in a
custom answer if I want, but I'm going
to go with build your own product. So,
it thinks a bit more. And is it okay,
it's asking me another question. What's
the use case? Let's go with the custom
PC builder. And what does it do now?
It's going to think a bit more. Uh,
should we enforce compatibility? Uh, how
about no more questions, please?
All right. So, uh, it's going to now
start working on a plan. And it's going
to do that as a markdown document that
we're going to be able to read and edit.
And that's also going to be a way of
tracking progress as we go through it.
So, it's uh, creating this plan for us.
It's uh thinking through exactly how to
do it. All right. So, it's created a
plan and um it's writing up the details
for us. And you'll notice we've got this
control Y to uh viewedit the plan. I've
sort of done something weird there. All
right. So, we will do a control Y. And
that's opened a
uh code instance over here. All right.
So, we can see the plan that it's
written. It's this build your own
product feature. uh it's got all this
kind of information. It's got the work
phases. It's got an example of the uh
impact on the files, the database schema
and so on. And if we were really doing a
feature of this size, we would probably
want to spend like a good hour iterating
on this design with the agent to refine
it into something that we're really
confident is going to produce the
outcome we want. One thing I often want
to do is tell it that I want to know how
to validate the work as it goes because
otherwise it just does a bunch of code
changes and I don't know whether it's
right or not. So, I'll go back over
here.
>> As you're doing that, I just want to
that has been such a like a tip that
I've learned from people and I'm glad
that it's becoming part of the standard
workflow is that plan, review the plan.
And that's really the time where I'm
most involved really is making sure that
the plan is what I want, right? Because
I'll see people complain that, hey, I
told AI to build a website and it built
it wrong. It's like,
>> well, if you just say build a website,
you didn't, you know what I mean? But if
you really give that, if you take your
time with the plan and think about that,
then you're kind of working a level up.
So, I just want to if people are kind of
like
not getting how important that is. I
think that's a really important step
there that you're showing.
>> 100% agreed. All right. So, so this is
one thing I often do is I tell it that I
want to know how to validate the work.
So you can see it started adding all
these validation entries at different
points. Now some of them I I I would
probably go back to it and say no I want
to be able to validate each thing in the
UI somehow organize your work so that I
can always see like something that the
user would be able to see. Anyway, once
you've refined that a bunch you then
tell it to start working and it's going
to update the plan as it goes. It will
mark things off as done as they're done
and this allows you to really retain
context over a long block of work. So
just to to show that um and this is
going to be a bit fake, but I'll tell it
um for testing mark all of phase one as
done. So it's going to think about that
for a second and then hopefully phase
one is going to get marked as done just
to show you that it can do that. It's
kind of obvious. There we go. So it's
marked those all as done and it would do
that while it's in the middle of its
work. All right. So that's an an example
of planning and we'll come back to do a
bit more with that application in a
minute. Um, so, uh, let's talk about
some of these other fundamental
abilities. And we're going to get into
skills and feedback here. So, what you
don't want to waste your time doing with
these systems is reinventing everything
from scratch every time you tell it what
to do. You want it to know how to be
effective within the context of your
application and with the technologies
that you already use uh, with readymade
capabilities and scripts and helpers and
things like that. And that's something
that skills can allow you to do. Let me
give you an example of skills. This is
another relatively new feature that's
just shipped in the last couple of
weeks. So, I'm going to come over here
and I'm going to start on that. So, I'm
going to go and show you how you can
install uh skills first. If I list the
skills that are available, you'll see
I've just got this one skill right now.
That's from a demo that we're going to
get to in a minute. So, just ignore that
for now. Pretend it's not there. and I'm
going to install some ready-made skills
that someone else has provided. So, I'm
going to go to plug-in marketplace and
list what marketplaces I've got.
Marketplaces are basically just git
repos. So, this one is one that
Anthropics has provided. And if I go
over to that repo, you'll see what
they've put in there. So, Anthropic has
provided this nice set of sample skills
for us. And we can go in there and see
them all. And we can go and see how
they're all implemented. I'll show you a
bit of how they're implemented in a
minute, but what a skill actually is,
it's a bunch of files that provides
context for an agent. So, it's a file
called skill.md that's got information
about how to do stuff. And it's got a
bit of header text here, this
description. And this is the important
and interesting part. Uh, AI models have
got a limited amount of context. So,
instead of dropping all of the skill
cont uh information into context, it
only puts this header part for each of
the skills. And that's just enough for
the agent to discover the skills there
and decide when it wants to use it. And
when it does, it can look up the full
details. So you can have tens, hundreds,
or thousands of skills and it won't blow
up the context window. It will look up
individual bits of information as it
goes.
>> Now, my understanding of that a little
bit, I used to put tons of information
in a copilot instructions
>> and I would include code snippets. I'd
include all this information. But then
the problem with that is that's part of
the context. It's
>> going back and forth in every request.
Okay, so with this you're just saying
here's how to generate a PDF
>> if you need it later. Go read the rest
of it and that's and then it's able to
just put that metadata in the context.
>> Exactly. And it's not just markdown
context. It can be actual helpers like
scripts and so on that it can invoke.
I'll show you that in a sec. So let's um
register the um the skills from this
marketplace. So, I'm going to install
something called document skills there.
And once I've done that, if I go back to
my list of skills, you can see I've got
now got all these things that you just
saw inside my web browser. And these
[laughter] persist across sessions. So,
if I uh create a new session and then
have a look at my skills now, you'll see
that I've still got all this stuff here.
So, let's have a go at using that. I'll
say use the Slack GIF creator skill to
make me a GIF about installing Copilot
CLI. All right. So, it's going to think
and that is going to use this skill from
here, the Slack GIF creator and this
contains some utilities like these
Python scripts here that it can use in
order to build the and so you see it's
reading them so it knows how to use
them. It's now making sure it's
installed whatever dependencies are
needed and then it's going to be able to
use that to create me a GIF hopefully.
Okay, so it's created a little script
that it now invokes
and it's checking the output. Let's just
quit that.
Yeah.
All right. So, let's see what it's just
created right now.
All right. So we check our timestamps.
So this was created literally just now.
Copilot CLI.GIF.
And if we want to view that, let's bring
that into our browser. And
nothing. Oh, it's a zero byte file. Oh
no, something's gone wrong. Okay. I
don't know what happened there. All
right.
>> If the [laughter] if the um skill had
worked correctly, it would have created
a file for us that would have worked.
You can see it tried, but there's
obviously something wrong with
>> maybe it was a tracking gif where it's
one pixel by one pixel. [laughter]
>> Well, it's zero kilobytes, so I think
nothing in there. All right. Anyway, you
get the idea that that's how to install
and use a skill. But the more
interesting bit is creating your own
skills. So, let's say that we want to
create a skill ourselves right now. So,
let's go back in here and we'll have a
look at how to do that. So firstly I've
just got all those skills from before
but now I want to use a skill called the
skill creator skill to create a skill.
Um and I'll tell it where to put it. It
should ask user which project uh we'll
do net spet core or github copilot
copilot cli no copilot SDK and we'll get
build status for that. All right so that
is going to discover that it's got a
skill creator skill. Hopefully it does.
And it's going to read in the details of
how to create skills
and then it's going to get started on
that. Hopefully.
All right. So, it's initializing the
skill. Now, let's have a look at the
code that it's producing as it does it.
So, it's just created this skill. Oh,
it's an empty file. Oops. Something's
not going wrong again.
What's going on?
The file is empty. Yes. Oh, okay. Fine.
It's done it now. Right. So, it's
populated the this skill and you can see
that it's got this description and it's
doing what I said about how things
should work. And we can read that and we
can edit it ourselves if we want to
change how that works. For example,
let's say I want it to only fetch build
status from the main branch. I could
edit it myself or I can just go back and
say actually only get status from main
and it edits it.
Has it finished editing? Oh, it's done
it now. Right. So, you can see it's just
added this thing here. U workflow runs
filter branch main. All right. So, we've
now got our skill.
All right. So, let's go out of there and
finally uh we can try and use it. So
let's see if we check what our list of
skills are. You can see we've now got
our build status skill and this has
stored in source control in our project
in this particular case. So we can share
it with other people on the team and
also it's now available as a slash
command. So you can get to it very
quickly with autocomp completion. So I
ask for build status and it's going to
think it's going to realize that there's
a skill that it needs to load into
context and it's choosing to ask the
user just like I said which project do
you want it for? Uh let's do it for uh
copilot SDK and it's now going to follow
the instructions that are in that skill.
Oh it's doing the large output handling
again. And
>> so that explicitly invoking is sorry to
interrupt.
>> That's great that you can explicitly
invoke it. I've I've noticed with MCPs
they'll have tools but you don't ever
really I mean you don't really directly
call a tool.
You can kind of hint but but here you're
actually able to with the slash command
say invoke this skill.
>> Yeah. In some cases some things that
support MTP do let you invoke them
directly. VS Code has a slash command
equivalent for MCP. Um, but yeah, I
would say it's very useful either way,
whether it's a skill or MCP or whatever.
If you know that's what you want it to
do, then why why type it out when you
can just get autocomp completion on the
slash.
>> Yeah.
>> Makes stuff easier for you.
>> So, just FYI, we've got a few good
comment or questions in here that I want
to take, but I don't want to interrupt
where you're at in the flow. So, if
now's good, I'll take them or later's
fine, too. All right, let's just finish
the uh this stuff about uh skills and
then we'll get to the questions.
All right, so
we've been looking at composition skills
and specialized tools, but the other
piece of this is the feedback loop. So
the another main antiattern that coding
agents get into is you tell them to do
something and they say, "I've done it."
And you ch try it and it doesn't work
and you say it doesn't work and it says,
"Oh, I'm sorry. I'll fix it. I've fixed
it now." And you try it and it still
doesn't work. and it says, "Oh, I'm
sorry. I'll fix it." And you try it and
it still doesn't work. And it's
incredibly annoying.
It's kind of like how other people feel
if they ask you to fix a bug in
software, but they don't specify it very
well, and you do some change, and then
the bug is still there. They're going to
think that you're not very smart for not
fixing the bug properly, but it's really
their fault for underspecifying or for
not being able to, you know, show you
what the bug really was. Same problem
happens with coding agents. If they
can't actually run your application,
they have a really hard time knowing
whether the change they've made is
right. So, anything you can do to give
it feedback will enable it to be more
successful. Allow it to invoke a
compiler, llinters, tests, whatever. But
even more than that, the ability to
actually run your application. This is
something we can achieve through skills
as well. So, I'm going to have a go at
doing that for um back for this simple
commerce application as well. Uh I've
already created a skill actually over
here called simple commerce automation
which teaches it how to in automate the
browser using playrite and all about how
to operate this particular web
application. Now obviously I didn't
write this myself. I got it out of the
skill creator wizard. Um I took me about
half an hour or something to keep
iterating until it had capabilities. It
knows how to log in as an admin. It
knows how to set up the site. It knows
how to um you know populate things. It
knows how to start the browser in the
first place. It knows how to discover
what links are on a page and things like
that. So using this skill I can do
something like the following.
Right. So let's just check firstly it's
loaded our skill and it has. You can see
that up there. So that being the case, I
can run it and let's just say start
browser.
So it'll think it'll load the skill into
context and hopefully it should know how
to start a browser now. So it runs uh
one of the scripts that are in there and
you can see a browser pops up for us.
Okay, cool. Now this browser is one that
it can automate. So I could go back to
it and give it some instruction like uh
I would like you to register a new user
Steve. Okay. So it thinks about how to
do that. It checks its instructions in
the skill there and then it should
hopefully be able to load that
capability in. And so it's using the
automate. There we go. It's done it. It
was a bit fast but you can see it says
hello Steve up there now. It's
successfully registered the user. Now,
the point of this is not for you to give
it instructions manually. The point is
that if you were getting it to work on a
feature, it can decide for itself to pop
open a browser and literally try it out
itself. And if it doesn't work, it can
then see what the problem was and go
back and fix it. So, for example, if we
were working on something to do with
order management, we might say, um, as
admin, create a new product. Um, let's
say super headphones.
uh then place five orders for it as
Steve. Actually, five separate orders.
All right. So, it's going to think about
that. That's quite a complicated process
for it to go through. Um but hopefully
using this skill, it's going to be able
to do all of that. So, it's generated a
script. What's it doing now? It's logged
in as an admin. It's is it going to
create a product for us? Oh, it's yes,
it's rapidly created the Super
Headphones product. Now, it's logged in
as Steve and it's placing a series of
orders for it and it can observe what's
going on. You know, it can use the
Chrome DevTools protocol to read the
contents of what's in the browser. Um,
if for some reason the order placement
fails, like there was a validation
error, whatever, it would be able to see
that. It would be able to go back to its
code and start fixing whatever it was
doing. So, does that make sense? this
idea of wiring up um a feedback loop.
>> Yeah, that's really cool. I I love that
whole like you're showing the cutting
out the repetitive nature of like
specify work, test it manually, all that
to be able to just say like you go
automate doing all of that. So, that's
great.
>> Awesome.
>> Wow.
>> Right. Um you wanted to ask any
questions?
>> Yeah. Okay. We've got a bunch here. Let
me see. Okay. Uh I'll go through some
quick ones. Um so is the CLI built with
Spectre console?
>> No, the CLI is implemented as a node
application with React Inc.
>> Okay. Uh can we get unlimited requests
>> if you have unlimited money? Yes.
[laughter]
>> Okay, great. Um let me see. Uh so this
goes back to we were talking about uh
GitHub
automating the GitHub CLI etc. Um and
just kind of mentioning here like uh
Azure DevOps. One thing that I've used
for this there's an Azure DevOps MCP
server um that's been pretty useful. So
just sharing.
>> Cool.
>> Um see uh how do you prompt it to create
the plan for review without having it
dive in and start making the changes
already? So basically
what plan mode is
>> sorry go ahead.
>> Oh sorry yeah I was speaking over you.
Uh yeah that's literally what plan mode
is. Plan mode is a is a mode that when
you are in it the agent is instructed
not to dive in and start implementing
stuff but only to work with you on the
plan document. Then you come back out of
that mode when you want it to start
making other code changes.
>> Great. Okay. Uh does plan mode remove
the need for tools like spec kit?
Um, plum mode is in a sense a very light
equivalent to spec kit. If you are using
spec kit and you're enjoying it and you
find that workflow to be what you want,
there's no reason you should stop doing
so. Uh, but I think that most people on
my team at least are feel that they're
they're doing good work using plan mode.
So, it's up to you.
>> Okay. A great comment from Winterfred
just uh likes to keep the plans inside
the repo. So then you you tell it create
them in a specific folder. Nice to be
able to kind of have that as an
artifact.
>> Yeah, that's another good workflow. A
lot of people do that. We don't do that
by default because
often these plan documents are quite
ephemeral like that. It's just I want to
work out how to make you do half an hour
of work successfully. It doesn't mean
that it's long-term documentation for
the project,
>> but in some cases it might be or it
might be that you go through a bunch of
planning in using the ephemeral document
and then at the end of it you say to it
something like add dev docs based on
this and then you know it will go and
look at that and work out what the the
long-term information is that you want
to store in source control and actually
writes that up as a nice document. Um
you can do it whatever way you want.
>> I I like that. That's something I've
kind of evolved into exactly is I'll say
explicitly do not create you know
temporary markdown documents and then at
the end of a work cycle say update the
you know official document on here's how
we do things or
>> cool
>> um are using claude opus 45 for a
specific reason it's a bit expensive for
the pro plan
>> um opus just produces amazingly good
results um I would say
if you can use it, it's great. Sauna is
very good as well though. Like I'm using
it because it's a luxury that we have
access to um on our team. But uh I think
there would be nothing stopping us from
being very productive with Sonnet as
well.
>> Uh so I know some tools I I for I don't
know if CLI has this but there's like an
auto mode um where it does auto
selection. Does CLI have that?
>> So by that you mean never ask me any
questions? Never prompt just
>> No, sorry. Um, model selection.
>> Oh, got it. Yeah. Um, well, in a sense
we do because the we pick a default
model for you every time you start a
session. Um,
>> but I don't think there's explicitly a
model called auto. Um, no, there isn't.
>> But yeah, if if there's a reason for it,
please give us a feature request.
>> That's uh something I've been like I've
noticed in um like in the SWE on on
GitHub.
>> Yeah. or just kind of generally is just
use the auto model and then it'll only
bump up to like Opus when it needs that,
>> you know, advanced thinking.
>> Um, do you always invoke skills
explicitly? I think you showed no, but I
just want
>> Yeah, you don't have to invoke them
explicitly. It's supposed to make its
own decisions about when to run them.
But if I'm doing a demo of a skill, I
might as well just like or if I
literally know that it's going to be a
specific skill and I know there's a
slash command for it, then it's fewer
keystrokes for me to for use it than not
>> or have it accidentally guess the wrong
thing and, you know, pick the wrong
skill, that sort of thing.
>> Uh, do slash commands allow reference
prompts? I'm using spec kit and I'm
unable to see prompts the same way I'm
able to reference skills.
Uh I don't think in copilot CLI we've
got a concept of predefined prompts like
that. If it's something you find useful
again please send us a feature request
and you know we can ship features like
that incredibly quickly.
>> Uh here's kind of a bigger question. I
think you kind of talked generally about
this but just to kind of get it out
there uh what is the difference between
skills and MCP?
Uh yeah, so MCP is the effectively a
protocol for communicating with some
external process. Um whereas skills is
just a bunch of context.
Okay,
>> that they're just different technically.
Like MCP is useful if you um if you have
some external service that you must
interact with, whereas uh skills is
useful if what you're trying to get it
to do can be reduced to a bunch of
information and Python scripts and so
on.
>> Okay. Um let me see. Will an agent
implicitly invoke skills if it thinks it
would be useful? I think you basically
covered this, but just
>> Yep.
>> Um, okay. And then this is just kind of
a general idea here. Sirly Dev, longtime
viewer here, um, says, uh, because of
software policies, they've been using
C-pilot to build a couple of utilities
here. They're talking about basically
wrapping things like SP who um and then
the next comment they said they're going
to be wanting to use um you know create
the skill for doing this with um copilot
copilot CLI as well.
>> Cool.
>> I think that's about all the um let me
see well
>> all right well I know we've coming up to
almost an hour and I still got another
cool thing I want to show so forwards a
little bit. But I want I'm going to
spend less time talking about uh you
know conceptual stuff and more about uh
let's let's talk about one other very
interesting bit of tech that's coming
out at the moment. So um Copilot CLI or
C-Pilot on the web coding agent whatever
you want or other coding agents you know
they're they all very helpful they give
you very um useful powers as a developer
when it comes to writing code. So that's
brilliant for you, but it's also
something that you can use to bring
additional powers into the products that
you make available to your customers as
well. And to enable that, we have very
recently shipped the copilot coding
agent SDK. And that allows you to use
our agent and all of its prompts and
tools and skills and so on within your
application to accomplish all this
stuff. So let me give you an example of
doing that. So let's get back to u this
thing of um
managing our own workflows. Let's say I
want to make a a little tool called
issue sizer and it's going to be
something that estimates the difficulty
of implementing particular issues that
have been filed against my repo. And I'm
going to do that using the GitHub
copilot SDK. So, I've installed the
current pre-release version of that and
then I'm going to be able to use it from
my .NET code. Now, from this slide, you
can see we've got SDKs currently for
Node, Python, Net, and Go. Those are the
official SDKs. There's also community
provided SDKs for Java, Rust, and C++.
I'm sure that list will keep growing
over time. Now, obviously, I'm going to
use the .NET one right now. And to do
this, it's pretty easy. I can start by
instantiating a copilot client here. And
this is going to use whatever instance
of copilot is installed on my machine
right now. We don't have a way of
bundling it yet, but we are looking at
doing that. And then I'm going to create
a session against that and I can then
use that to do stuff like I can say list
the files in this directory. I don't
have to tell it how to do that because
it is the coding agent. It's got all the
tools that the coding agent has.
Obviously, it knows how to find files on
disk. So, if I run this now, then
hopefully we'll see that produce some
useful output. If a terminal window
appears, here it does.
Okay. Now, this might take a moment the
first time that it has to run. It always
does the first time I run it. Um, that's
going to be going through the all of the
flows that the coding agent would do to
look at the files on disk and decide how
to respond to you. And we'll get a
little bit more insights into how it
works in a minute once it's finished
responding. There we go. So you can see
that that was running in the context of
the build output directory. And so it's
telling us about all the DLS and stuff
that it managed to find in there. All
right. But it took a while and we didn't
get any obvious feedback on the screen.
So to get a bit more information, we can
subscribe to events. So we've got
session.on and then we'll get events
back. And there are about 20 different
types of events. They've all got nice
strongly typed .NET classes to represent
them. For now, I'm just going to look at
tool executions and then everything
else. And I'm just going to log all this
stuff to the console when it happens. So
if I run that again now, then instead of
showing us no output while it works,
we're going to start to see this stream
of events that are taking place. Uh we
can see that it's reporting its intent
of listing directory contents. It's
using a tool to look at the files on
disk and then eventually it comes back
with its response to us. All right,
cool. So that's some of the basics. Uh
so you can use that if you want to
automate the CLI like you can send
messages in, you can receive messages
back and automate things. But you can
also plug in your own capabilities uh in
uh an even better way by just providing
functions that it can call. So here I am
going to use a normal C# function to
create uh this function here called get
issue size label that will take in a
number of days work and then it uses
this absolutely outrageous syntax. What
on earth is that? To uh return different
strings depending on what that value is
and I can plug that into my session up
here. So here I'm going to say uh I'm
going to use the Microsoft extensions AI
helpers here to turn that uh net method
into an AI function that our copilot
agent is going to be able to call. So to
prove that it actually does, let's put a
break point there. And we better change
our prompt to make it use that. What's
the label for an issue that takes six
days? I'll run that with the debugger.
And hopefully it will start up. It will
start the session. and it will start
thinking about how to satisfy the
users's requests and it will decide
presumably to call that net method.
There we go. It's done it and it's
passed in six days work. We're going to
return size m from that and it's going
to say the the issue is size m. All
right. Cool. So that's all very well.
But the more important thing here is
that we can now chain this together with
all the other capabilities that built
into the coding agent by default. So for
example, I could implement a whole thing
that's going to uh produce uh estimates
of how long it takes to implement stuff.
So now I've given it this prompt saying
you're a software engineer. Check if the
issue corresponds to source code in this
directory. investigate the existing code
and provide an accurate estimate of the
size uh respond in this particular
format. All right, so let's run that.
See if it works. Going to need to have
an issue to uh estimate the size of.
So let's go and find something.
It's the wrong one.
Where's my other browser?
Here it is. Right. So I'm going to go
into copilot SDK which is open source
and let's find some issue that we can
estimate the difficulty of.
Let's have
connect to active CLI session. That's
going to be a difficult one. So
I'll paste that in. Paste. There we go.
All right. And you can see that it's
going to start using all of its agent
smarts to decide uh how to get
information about that. It's going to do
a web fetch. It's going to be comparing
that to the source code on disk which
doesn't even match that repo. So it'll
give up on that pretty quickly. And then
eventually hopefully it will call our
tool to get the size label and it's
going to provide a nice response for us.
Okay. So it's come up with size large
implementing an interactive diff tool is
large and so on. Yeah, that's probably
true. All right. Cool. All right. So
overall point of this is that uh this is
a higher level way to interact with AI
rather than just using something like a
plain chat completion endpoint. You can
use the whole agentic loop that copilot
comes with the same one that's used in
the CLI and that's used on the web and
all of the built-in prompts that we've
been carefully optimizing and
benchmarking for months now. Uh and
bring that kind of smartness into your
project.
Cool. Um that's enough about that. Um,
yeah. Any other questions or things you
want to bring up, John?
>> Yeah, there were a few. Um, let me see.
There's tons of questions. I'm actually
trying to pick the the top here. Um, is
there a tool that can price out plans?
This was talking about, I think, you
know, like the different models and
stuff.
>> Uh, price out the plans of using
Copilot. Is that
>> I think so. Yeah. I don't think we have
something like that, but that would be a
really interesting thing to do. On the
other hand, how would you even run it if
you don't already have Copilot? Um
maybe we should uh put that up on the
web somewhere. Yeah, it's an interesting
idea. I don't think that we've got that.
Ideally, our documentation would be
clear enough that you don't even need AI
to tell you what the price is going to
be. Um if it's not, please complain at
us and then we'll start poking people to
do something about that. It does sound
interesting though like taking metadata
about you know different things and
saying like here's my planned document
for this thing like give me some
estimates and like help me you know make
that um that sounds like a skill or
something.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
okay this is a question about um from
Danielle loves copilot and SDK wondering
about agent framework.
>> Yeah.
>> Um what's the value prop between the
different things?
>> Yeah. So we've got a little sort of
stack of like higher and lower level
things now I suppose in net
specifically. So the lowest level thing
in net for this stuff would be the
Microsoft extensions AI libraries which
give you raw access to the chat
completion endpoints which is a pretty
thin layer on top of the the language
models themselves. And the these have no
opinions about what kind of tasks to do,
what tools should be available, what
prompts should be available, what
workflows it should follow or anything
to do with that. It's got no opinions
about any of it. And if that's what you
want, if you want to provide all that
logic yourself, then going in directly
at the chat completion layer is the one
for you. Higher level thing on top of
that is agent framework. that defines
this notion of agents that are stateful,
that you can have an ongoing
conversation with, and that potentially
know how to interact with each other to
distribute work among themselves, but
it's still unopinionated about what kind
of work it is that they do. And a more
high level thing on top of that would be
well it's not on top of it it's actually
separately implemented but a more high
level thing would be the copilot SDK
which is not just an agent but it's
specifically the coding agent that we've
optimized uh for solving realistic
largecale difficult professional
software tasks and it's got all the
tools needed to find files on disk look
stuff up on GitHub um you know be able
to keep track of what permissions you've
given to it the ability to uh start up
MCP servers and interact with skills and
you know all the things that Copilot CLI
does um but oriented around uh coding
scenarios you can actually remove all
the coding specific stuff from it if you
want to when you create one of these
sessions with um this stuff here in
addition to just passing tools into it
you can also say excluded tools and then
you can remove stuff that's coding agent
related if you want to you can also pass
a system message
and I wonder if I remember that content
equals
and then we could say uh mode equals
modereplace.
Yeah. So the default mode for system
messages append. So that would be adding
additional system message content to all
the stuff that's default for copilot
CLI. But if you change it to replace
then it throws away all the built-in
prompts completely and uh you know now
your instruction the are the only
instructions it would use. So it's up to
you really whether you want to use that
stuff or not. Would it be like at a
simple level would it be okay to say
that the most natural fit for co-pilot
is as an agent more in the development
role whereas agent framework I would
think to use that more in integrating
into my application.
Well while you could move you can do
anything with anything. It seems like
more natural fit
>> maybe. Now it depends how much stuff you
want to work out by yourself. So getting
creating some some kind of agent from
scratch is easy. You can do it in 10
minutes probably. But is it going to
behave well? What's the difference
between something that behaves well and
doesn't? Well, it's like world-class
expertise in prompt engineering and
months of very expensive benchmarking.
And that's what's gone into all of the
stuff that we're shipping in Copilot
SDK. So if you want to make it up
yourself, go for it. But if you want to
build on this incredibly wellproven um
battle tested agent that knows how to
make good judgments about how much work
to do about stuff and and how to pick
between different tools and things like
that, then Copilot SDK is a great point
starting point for that. And it's not
although out of the box it's oriented
around software development tasks, it's
not a big step to give it instructions
to do other things. Like if you want to
make a something that's going to process
all your emails and decide what like
important tasks to do or something like
that, the coding agent is going to do a
really good job of that pretty much out
of the box. Um, I don't know about the
rest of the people on this call, but I
know that I and all the other people on
my team use Copilot CLI to do a lot of
things that are not coding related.
Like, if I have to do anything on my
computer that's more than a few clicks,
I would just tell C-Pilot CLI to do it.
If I need to write some documentation,
I'm going to tell Copilot CLI to do it.
If I have to, you know, process a lot of
files of of any kind for any reason,
again, going to be using the CLI. Um, so
yeah, it's a very flexible tool.
One more related question here and just
Wifred saying if you're integrating aic
features into products and I guess what
I'm thinking of if I'm shipping software
or I'm putting software on a server
would I kind of think of that more as
agent framework versus copilot CLI or
SDK for running on my machine
locally to do a task for me.
>> Yeah, it could be. Yeah. So certainly at
the moment with Copilot SDK, we're we're
optimized the the thing around uh stuff
that just runs for you with your
credentials on your machine. Uh it's
definitely not oriented around running
on a server with you know shared
credentials and uh you know sessions
that span multiple users and things like
that. I think we will get to that point
and probably very soon but right now
we're not at that point. So um so
certainly at the moment you'd be better
off with agent framework for that. Um
but I would imagine that these things
are just going to co-evolve and it might
be that they end up solving similar pro
problems in certain cases and that's
fine. You know people will just pick uh
what thing is a good match for whatever
they're doing and if you're using our
stuff we're not we're not trying to push
you to one or the other like whatever is
good for you.
>> Okay. Um, last question and kind of
along that line generally because we're
talking to dev audience that I think is
more used to Visual Studio or VS Code.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, I like this from Alexander. What's
the difference from CLI and Copilot in
VS or VS Code? So, I want to reframe
this a bit more as a question to you're
talking to developers who are probably
experienced with using Copilot in VS or
VS Code. Y
>> and you've shown a ton of compelling
stuff, but like kind of the takeaway to
hey, give this a shot, try it out. What
how would you kind of wrap that up?
>> Yeah, that that is what I would say. So,
I would say that my my call to action
for everyone from this is is just to
give it a go and specifically to try
doing something that you wouldn't
normally do because then you'll get a
sense of this like, oh my goodness, I
just did that. Like an example of uh of
that for me in the last week was uh I
was using this screen recording software
and it had a bug where it would just
crash when I did a certain thing which
is kind of annoying. I I found it it's
git repo and I was about to file an
issue with it because I wasn't like
going to do anything about it myself. It
was written in Rust and I don't even
speak Rust. So I was about to file an
issue and I thought why file an issue?
Let's just try doing this myself. I
opened copilot CLI. I told it to clone I
didn't even clone the reper. I just said
clone this repo. fix this bug and submit
a pull request. And it literally did it
like in less than 10 minutes. It cloned
the repo, it diagnosed the problem, it
fixed it, it submitted a pull request
with a nice write up and the next day
that change was actually merged into the
project. And that for me was like a
pretty amazingly empowering moment. I
can just do stuff like that now. And so,
so that's my recommendation is try doing
something that you wouldn't normally do.
Prototype a thing that you've been
putting off for a while. implement a
crazy feature in your software that you
wouldn't think that you've normally got
time for, just give it a go and just see
how quickly you're able to make progress
with that. If you want to do stuff
inside VS or VS Code, that's absolutely
fine. Um, but I think it's worth giving
a go to the CLI. It's weirdly addictive.
I don't know what it is about the the
way that the UI works, the way that the
agent is set up. Something about it just
feels really successful. So give it a go
and um yeah see see how it goes for you.
>> Last last thing, can you um show us okay
I'm convinced how do we actually get
started? Where's the best place to go to
kind of learn about installing and
setting up copilot CLI?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So you can go to the this
git repo github/copilot
CLI currently in public preview and
that's where you'll find all the
documentation and where you will find
the getting started steps. So you can
see what platforms are supported. Uh you
can see you can install it through
Winger if you want to. I think Scott
Hansen just put it on the Windows Store
as well. Um or on all platforms you can
install it through npm as well if you
want to. So there's plenty of easy ways
to get started with that and uh then
hopefully that will step you through all
the process of authenticating and and
getting going.
>> Awesome. Okay,
this has been fascinating. Thanks for
all the amazing demos. Uh um great. I'll
I'll let you go. Thanks for all the
great questions, too, everybody.
>> Awesome.
>> So, and we'll be back with our regular
scheduled host, Bruno, uh next week, and
I'll play the Thanks for watching song.
Bye, folks.
>> Bye.